<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<?xml-model href="cornwallis.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<surrender><persons>Gen. Cornwallis to Gen. Washington</persons>, <date when="1781-10-18"><month>October</month>
        <day>18</day>, <year>1781</year></date>
    <paragraph n="1" topic="agree">I agree to open a treaty of capitulation upon the basis of the
        garrisons of York and Gloucester, including seamen, being prisoners of war, without annexing
        the condition of their being sent to Europe; but I expect to receive a compensation in the
        articles of capitulation for the surrender of Gloucester in its present state of defence. </paragraph>
    <paragraph n="2" topic="conditions">I shall, in particular, desire, <condition j="1"
            kind="materials">that the Bonetta <ship>sloop of war</ship> may be left entirely at my
            disposal<!-- I wanted to tag all of the types of conditions that Lord Cornwallis requests starting here--></condition>,
        from the hour that the capitulation is signed, <condition j="2" kind="messenger">to receive
            an <carrier>aid-de-camp</carrier> to carry my dispatches to <receiver>Sir Henry
                Clinton</receiver>.</condition>
        <condition j="3" kind="soldiers">Such soldiers as I may think proper to send as passengers
            in her, to be manned with fifty men of her own crew</condition>, <condition j="4"
            kind="travel">and to be permitted to sail without examination</condition>, when my
        dispatches are ready: engaging, on my part, that the ship shall be brought back and
        delivered to you, if she escapes the dangers of the sea, <condition j="5" kind="soldiers"
            >that the crew and soldiers shall be accounted for in future exchanges</condition>, that
        she shall carry off no officer without your consent, nor public property of any kind; and I
        shall likewise desire, <condition j="6" kind="property">that the traders and inhabitants may
            preserve their property</condition>, <condition j="7" kind="civilians">and that no
            person may be punished or molested for having joined the British troops</condition>. </paragraph>
    <paragraph n="3" topic="meet">If you choose to proceed to negociation on these grounds, I shall
        appoint two field officers of my army to meet two officers from you, at any time and place
        that you think proper, to digest the articles of capitulation.</paragraph></surrender>
